I essentially drag sledges for a living,
أنا أقوم أساسًا بسحب الزلاجات للعيش،
so it doesn't take an awful lot to flummox me intellectually,
فهي لا تأخذ مني جهدًا فكريًا كثيرًا،
but I'm going to read this question
لكن سوف أقرأ لكم هذا السؤال
from an interview earlier this year:
من مقابلة حدثت مسبقًا هذا العام:
"Philosophically, does the constant supply of information
"من جهة فلسفية، هل الإمداد الثابت للمعلومة
steal our ability to imagine
يجعلنا نفقد قدرتنا على التخيل
or replace our dreams of achieving?
أو يحل محل أحلامنا التي نريد تحقيقها؟
After all, if it is being done somewhere by someone,
لأنها في النهاية، تحصل في مكان ما عن طريق شخص ما،
and we can participate virtually,
ونحن نستطيع المشاركة عن بعد،
then why bother leaving the house?"
فلماذا نتعب أنفسنا بالخروج من المنزل؟"
I'm usually introduced as a polar explorer.
أنا عادة معروف بأنني مستكشف قطبي.
I'm not sure that's the most progressive or 21st-century
لست متأكدًا إن كان هذا يعتبر عملًا متقدمًا أو يواكب القرن 21
of job titles, but I've spent more than two percent now
لكنني أمضيت أكثر من 2 بالمئة من حياتي
of my entire life living in a tent inside the Arctic Circle,
أعيش في خيمة في دائرة القطب الشمالي،
so I get out of the house a fair bit.
خرجت من منزلي خائفًا قليلًا.
And in my nature, I guess, I am a doer of things
وفي طبيعتي، أعتقد أنني أحب فعل الأشياء
more than I am a spectator or a contemplator of things,
أكثر من كوني متفرجًا أو متأملًا لها،
and it's that dichotomy, the gulf between ideas and action
وذلك الانقسام، الخليج ما بين الأفكار والأفعال
that I'm going to try and explore briefly.
التي تجعلني أحاول واستكشف بإيجاز.
The pithiest answer to the question "why?"
والجواب الأبلغ على السؤال "لماذا؟"
that's been dogging me for the last 12 years
والذي كان يحيرني للسنوات ال12 الأخيرة
was credited certainly to this chap, the rakish-looking gentleman
والذي يعود الفضل إليه هو هذا الشاب ، ذو المظهر الفارع
standing at the back, second from the left,
الواقف هناك في الخلف ، الثاني من اليسار
George Lee Mallory. Many of you will know his name.
جورج لي مالوري . كثير منكم سوف يعرف اسمه.
In 1924 he was last seen disappearing into the clouds
في عام 1924 شوهد آخر مرة يختفي بين السحب
near the summit of Mt. Everest.
بالقرب من قمة ايفرست.
He may or may not have been the first person to climb Everest,
قد يكون أول من تسلق جبل ايفرست وقد لا يكون،
more than 30 years before Edmund Hillary.
أكثر من ثلاثين عاماُ قبل ايدموند هيلاري
No one knows if he got to the top. It's still a mystery.
لا أحد يعلم إذا اكان قد وصل إلى القمة، هذا لا يزال لغزًا.
But he was credited with coining the phrase, "Because it's there."
لكن الفضل يعود له في وضع المثل، " لأنه هناك. "
Now I'm not actually sure that he did say that.
الآن أنا لست متأكداً إذا كان هو من قال هذا الكلام.
There's very little evidence to suggest it, but what he did say
هناك دليل صغير يدعم هذا، لكن ما قاله هو
is actually far nicer,
في الحقيقة أجمل بكثير،
and again, I've printed this. I'm going to read it out.
ومرة أخرى، لقد طبعت هذا وسوف أقرأه.
"The first question which you will ask
"السؤال الأول والذي سوف تسأله
and which I must try to answer is this:
والذي يجب أن أحاول الإجابة عنه هو:
What is the use of climbing Mt. Everest?
ما الفائدة من تسلق جبل ايفرست؟
And my answer must at once be, it is no use.
وجوابي مرةً واحدة، أنه لا توجد أي فائدة من ذلك.
There is not the slightest prospect of any gain whatsoever.
لا يوجد أقل ما يمكن من الكسب في أي حال من الأحوال.
Oh, we may learn a little about the behavior
أوه ، قد نتعلم شيء بسيط عن سلوك
of the human body at high altitudes,
جسم الإنسان في الأماكن المرتفعة،
and possibly medical men may turn our observation
وبإمكان رجال الطب أن يحولوا ملاحظاتنا هذه
to some account for the purposes of aviation,
إلى بعض الاستعدادات التي قد تنفذ عند الطيران،
but otherwise nothing will come of it.
ولكن غير هذا لن يحدث شيء آخر.
We shall not bring back a single bit of gold or silver,
نحن لا يفترض بنا العودة ولو بشيء قليل من الذهب أو الفضة،
and not a gem, nor any coal or iron.
ولا بجوهرة واحدة، أو أي شيء من الفحم أو الحديد.
We shall not find a single foot of earth that can be planted
نحن لا يجب أن نجد مقدار قدم واحد من الأرض التي قد يزرع
with crops to raise food. So it is no use.
بها المحاصيل لإنتاج الغذاء. لذا لا يوجد فائدة من ذلك.
If you cannot understand that there is something in man
إذا لم تستطع الفهم بأن هناك شيء في الرجل
which responds to the challenge of this mountain
والذي يستجيب لتحدي هذا الجبل
and goes out to meet it, that the struggle
ويخرج لملاقاته، هذا النضال
is the struggle of life itself upward and forever upward,
هو نضال الحياة نفسها في الصعود ودائماً في الصعود،
then you won't see why we go.
إذاً انت لن تر لماذا نذهب.
What we get from this adventure is just sheer joy,
ما نجد من هذه المغامرة هو مجرد السعادة،
and joy, after all, is the end of life.
والسعادة في الأخير هي منتهى الحياة.
We don't live to eat and make money.
نحن لا نعيش لنأكل و نجمع المال.
We eat and make money to be able to enjoy life.
نحن نأكل و نجمع المال حتى نستطيع الاستمتاع بالحياة.
That is what life means, and that is what life is for."
هذا ما تعنيه الحياة، وهذا ما تكون له الحياة."
Mallory's argument that leaving the house,
نقاش مولاري حول الخروج من المنزل ،
embarking on these grand adventures is joyful and fun,
والشروع في هذه المغامرات العظيمة هو مبهج وممتع،
however, doesn't tally that neatly with my own experience.
عمومًا، هذا لا ينسجم مع تجربتي أنا.
The furthest I've ever got away from my front door
أبعد ما ذهبت إليه من باب منزلي
was in the spring of 2004. I still don't know exactly
كان في ربيع عام 2004. لا أزال لا أعلم بالتحديد
what came over me, but my plan was to make
ماذا جرى لي، ولكن خطتي كانت هو أن أقوم
a solo and unsupported crossing of the Arctic Ocean.
برحلة فردية و غير مدعومة لأقطع المحيط المتجمد الشمالي.
I planned essentially to walk from the north coast of Russia
خططت مبدأيًا لأمشي من الساحل الشمالي لروسيا
to the North Pole, and then to carry on to the north coast of Canada.
إلى القطب الشمالي، ثم أستمر إلى الساحل الشمالي لكندا.
No one had ever done this. I was 26 at the time.
لم يسبق لأي أحد أن قام بمثل هذا من قبل. لقد كان عمري 26 عاما.
A lot of experts were saying it was impossible,
الكثير من الخبراء كانوا يقولون أن هذا مستحيل،
and my mum certainly wasn't very keen on the idea.
ولم تكن أمي مرتاحة لهذه الفكرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The journey from a small weather station on the north coast
الرحلة من محطة طقس صغيرة في الساحل الشمالي
of Siberia up to my final starting point,
لسيبريا حتى نقطة النهاية،
the edge of the pack ice, the coast of the Arctic Ocean,
حافة رزمة ثلجية، ساحل القطب المتجمد الشمالي،
took about five hours, and if anyone watched fearless
استغرقت حوالي 5 ساعات، إذا كان أحد قد رأى "فيرليس"
Felix Baumgartner going up, rather than just coming down,
فيليكس بومغارتنر يصعد إلى أعلى، بدل النزول فقط،
you'll appreciate the sense of apprehension,
سوف تقدر حاسة التخوف،
as I sat in a helicopter thundering north,
وعند جلوسي في المروحية وهي ترعد شمالا،
and the sense, I think if anything, of impending doom.
وفي لحظة، أحسست أنني على وشك الهلاك.
I sat there wondering what on Earth I had gotten myself into.
جلست هناك أفكر ما الذي وضعت نفسي فيه.
There was a bit of fun, a bit of joy.
كان هناك بعض المتعة والبهجة.
I was 26. I remember sitting there
كنت في ال26 من عمري. أتذكر جلوسي هناك
looking down at my sledge. I had my skis ready to go,
انظر إلى زلاجاتي . وقد كانت جاهزة،
I had a satellite phone, a pump-action shotgun
كان معي جهاز اتصال عن طريق الأقمار الصناعية وبندقية
in case I was attacked by a polar bear.
في حال هوجمت من قبل دب قطبي.
I remember looking out of the window and seeing the second helicopter.
أتذكر عندما كنت أنظر من النافذه لأرى المروحية الأخرى.
We were both thundering through this incredible Siberian dawn,
كنا جميعاً نمضي خلال هذا الفجر السيبيري الرائع،
and part of me felt a bit like a cross between Jason Bourne
وجزء مني أحس قليلا بتقاطع جايسون بورن
and Wilfred Thesiger. Part of me
وويلفريد ثيسيجر. جزء مني
felt quite proud of myself, but mostly I was just utterly terrified.
أحسست بالفخر بنفسي، ولكن كنت مرتعباً أكثر.
And that journey lasted 10 weeks, 72 days.
واستغرقت الرحلة 10 أسابيع ، 72 يوماً.
I didn't see anyone else. We took this photo next to the helicopter.
لم أر أي شخص آخر. أخذنا هذا الصورة بالقرب من المروحيه.
Beyond that, I didn't see anyone for 10 weeks.
بعد ذلك ، لم أرى أي شخص لمدة 10 أسابيع.
The North Pole is slap bang in the middle of the sea,
القطب الشمالي كان صفعة في وسط البحر،
so I'm traveling over the frozen surface of the Arctic Ocean.
إذاً أنا أسافر على سطح المحيط الشمالي المتجمد.
NASA described conditions that year as the worst since records began.
ناسا وصفت أوضاع تلك السنة بأنها الأسوأ منذ أن بدأت تسجل أوضاع الطقس هناك.
I was dragging 180 kilos of food and fuel and supplies,
كنت أسحب 180 كيلو من الغذاء والوقود والإمدادات،
about 400 pounds. The average temperature for the 10 weeks
حوالي 400 باوند. متوسط درجة الحرارة لفترة 10 اسابيع
was minus 35. Minus 50 was the coldest.
كانت سالب 35 . سالب 50 كانت أبرد درجة.
So again, there wasn't an awful lot of joy or fun to be had.
إذاً مرة أخرى، لم يكن هناك الكثير من الفرح أو المتعة لتحصل عليها.
One of the magical things about this journey, however,
واحد من الأشياء السحرية عن هذه الرحلة، عمومًا،
is that because I'm walking over the sea,
هو أنني أمشي على البحر،
over this floating, drifting, shifting crust of ice
مع هذا الطفو والتزحلق وتحرك قطع الثلج
that's floating on top of the Arctic Ocean is
التي تطفو على المحيط المتجمد الشمالي
it's an environment that's in a constant state of flux.
البيئة تكون في تدفق دائم.
The ice is always moving, breaking up, drifting around,
الثلج دائماً يتحرك ويتكسر ويتزلحق،
refreezing, so the scenery that I saw for nearly 3 months
ويعاود التجمد، لذا المشهد المتكرر لثلاثة أشهر
was unique to me. No one else will ever, could ever,
كان مميزا. لا أحد آخر يمكنه أو سوف يمكنه،
possibly see the views, the vistas, that I saw for 10 weeks.
مشاهدة هذا المنظر، وتلك الآفاق ،شاهدتها لمدة 10 أسابيع.
And that, I guess, is probably the finest argument for leaving the house.
والتي أعتقد أنها أفضل شيء يجعلك تغادر المنزل.
I can try to tell you what it was like,
لا أستطيع حتى محاولة أن أصف لكم كيف كانت،
but you'll never know what it was like,
ولن تستطيعوا أبداً أن تعرفوا كيف كانت،
and the more I try to explain that I felt lonely,
وعند الزيادة في محاولة شرح كم كنت وحيدًا،
I was the only human being in 5.4 million square-miles,
لقد كنت الإنسان الوحيد في محيط 5.4 مليون متر مربع،
it was cold, nearly minus 75 with windchill on a bad day,
لقد كان الجو بارداً جداً، حوالي سالب 75 مع رياح ثلجية في يوم سيء،
the more words fall short, and I'm unable to do it justice.
الكلمات تعجز عن الوصف، أنا لا أستطيع أن أعطيها حقها.
And it seems to me, therefore, that the doing,
وقد اتضح لي أن هذا هو الفعل الصحيح،
you know, to try to experience, to engage, to endeavor,
تعلمون جميعًا، لتخوض تجربة ولتلتحم معها و لتسعى إليها،
rather than to watch and to wonder, that's where
بدلاً من مشاهدتها أو السؤال عنها، هناك
the real meat of life is to be found,
حيث القيمة الحقيقية للحياة،
the juice that we can suck out of our hours and days.
عصارة ساعاتنا وأيامنا.
And I would add a cautionary note here, however.
وأود أن أضيف ملاحظة تحذيرية هنا.
In my experience, there is something addictive
في تجربتي، كان هناك إدمان
about tasting life at the very edge of what's humanly possible.
على تذوق طعم الحياة في الحافة التي بالكاد يصل إليها الإنسان.
Now I don't just mean in the field of
أنا لا أعني فقط في مجال
daft macho Edwardian style derring-do,
فتل العضلات الإدواردي،
but also in the fields of pancreatic cancer,
ولكن أيضاً في مجال سرطان البنكرياس،
there is something addictive about this, and in my case,
هنالك شيء يدعوك للإدمان على هذا، وفي قضيتي،
I think polar expeditions are perhaps not that far removed
أعتقد أن الاستكشافات القطبية لسيت بهذا البعد
from having a crack habit.
عن إدمان المخدرات.
I can't explain quite how good it is until you've tried it,
لا أستطيع أن أشرح لكم كم كانت جيدةً حتى تجربوها،
but it has the capacity to burn up all the money I can get my hands on,
وقد كان لها القدرة على صرف كل ما أمكنني جمعه من المال،
to ruin every relationship I've ever had,
وقطع كل علاقه مع أي شخص كانت لدي،
so be careful what you wish for.
لذا كن حذراً مما تتمناه.
Mallory postulated that there is something in man
مالوري اقترح أن هناك شيء في الرجل
that responds to the challenge of the mountain,
يستجيب للتحدي في الجبل،
and I wonder if that's the case whether there's something
وأتساءل إذا كان هناك شيء
in the challenge itself, in the endeavor, and particularly
في التحدي نفسه وفي السعي، وبالتحديد
in the big, unfinished, chunky challenges that face humanity
في التحديات الكبيرة والغير منتهية والتي تواجه البشر
that call out to us, and in my experience that's certainly the case.
والتي تنادينا، وفي تجربتي هذه هي القضية.
There is one unfinished challenge
هناك تحد واحد لم ينتهِ بعد
that's been calling out to me for most of my adult life.
والذي كان يناديني في أغلب حياتي الراشدة.
Many of you will know the story.
الكثير منكم سيعرف القصة.
This is a photo of Captain Scott and his team.
هذه هي الصور للكابتن سكوت وفريقه.
Scott set out just over a hundred years ago to try
سكوت كان قبل 100 عام يحاول
to become the first person to reach the South Pole.
حتى يكون أول شخص ليصل إلى القطب المتجمد الجنوبي.
No one knew what was there. It was utterly unmapped
لا أحد يعلم ماذا كان هناك. لقد كان مجهولًا تمامًا
at the time. We knew more about the surface of the moon
في ذلك الوقت. عرفنا الكثير عن سطح القمر
than we did about the heart of Antarctica.
أكثر مما عرفنا عن قلب القارة المتجمدة الجنوبية.
Scott, as many of you will know, was beaten to it
سكوت، كما سوف يعلم الكثير منكم، كان موجهًا لها
by Roald Amundsen and his Norwegian team,
عن طريق روالد امندسن وفريقه،
who used dogs and dogsleds. Scott's team were on foot,
والذين استخدموا الكلاب لتجر الزلاجات. فريق سكوت كانوا على الأقدام،
all five of them wearing harnesses and dragging around sledges,
كل الخمسة منهم يرتدون ملابس ثقيلة ويسحبون الزلاجات،
and they arrived at the pole to find the Norwegian flag already there,
ووصلوا إلى القطب الجنوبي ليجدوا العلم النرويجي قبلهم هناك،
I'd imagine pretty bitter and demoralized.
أتصور مدى الإحباط والمرارة الذي وجدوه.
All five of them turned and started walking back to the coast
الخمسة جميعهم التفوا وعادوا إلى الساحل
and all five died on that return journey.
ومات الخمسة جميعهم وهم في طريق العودة.
There is a sort of misconception nowadays that
هناك شيء من خلط المفاهيم اليوم
it's all been done in the fields of exploration and adventure.
كلها حصلت في مجال الاسكشاف و المغامرة.
When I talk about Antarctica, people often say,
عندما أتكلم عن القارة المتجمدة الجنوبية، الناس دائماً يقولون،
"Hasn't, you know, that's interesting,
"ألم، تعلم، ذلك مثير للاهتمام،
hasn't that Blue Peter presenter just done it on a bike?"
لكن ألم يقم مقدم بلو بيتر ذاك بالقيام بذلك على دراجة؟"
Or, "That's nice. You know, my grandmother's going
أو "هذا جميل، كما تعلم، جدتي ذاهبة
on a cruise to Antarctica next year. You know.
على متن سفينة رحلات إلى القارة المتجمدة الجنوبية في السنة القادمة.
Is there a chance you'll see her there?"
هل هناك أي فرصة لرؤيتها هناك؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But Scott's journey remains unfinished.
ولكن رحلة سكوت تبقى غير منتهية.
No one has ever walked from the very coast of Antarctica
لم يستطع أحد أبدًا أن يمضي من الساحل البعيد للقارة المتجمدة الجنوبية
to the South Pole and back again.
إلى القطب الجنوبي ويعود.
It is, arguably, the most audacious endeavor
هذا، وهو قابل للنقاش، المسعى الأكثر جرأة
of that Edwardian golden age of exploration,
في الفترة الذهبية الإدوارديه في الاستكشاف،
and it seemed to me high time, given everything
وتبدو لي وقتا عظيما، باعتبار كل شيء
we have figured out in the century since
قد استنتجناه في هذا القرن منذ
from scurvy to solar panels, that it was high time
من الاسقريوط إلى الألواح الشمسية، ذاك وقت عظيم
someone had a go at finishing the job.
شخص ما يجب أن ينهي العمل.
So that's precisely what I'm setting out to do.
وهذا هو بالتحديد ما أحاول عمله.
This time next year, in October, I'm leading a team of three.
في مثل هذا الوقت من السنة القادمة، في أكتوبر، سوف أتزعم فريقا من ثلاثة أشخاص .
It will take us about four months to make this return journey.
سوف يستغرق منا حوالي 4 أشهر لنقوم بهذه الرحلة.
That's the scale. The red line is obviously halfway to the pole.
هذا هو المقياس. الخط الأحمر كما هو واضح هو نصف الطريق إلى القطب.
We have to turn around and come back again.
يجب علينا الالتفاف و العودة.
I'm well aware of the irony of telling you that we will be
أنا على علم بسخرية أن أقول لكم بأننا سوف
blogging and tweeting. You'll be able to live
نتواصل معكم عن طريق التدوين والتغريد. ستكونون قادرين على عيش
vicariously and virtually through this journey
الرحلة بشكل افتراضي
in a way that no one has ever before.
بطريقة لم يقم بها أي شخص من قبل.
And it'll also be a four-month chance for me to finally
وسوف تكون أخيرا فرصة من أربعة شهور لي
come up with a pithy answer to the question, "Why?"
لأحصل على جواب السؤال "لماذا ؟"
And our lives today are safer and more comfortable
وحياتنا اليوم أكثر أمانا وراحة
than they have ever been. There certainly isn't much call
مما كانت عليه من قبل. لا يوجد هناك الكثير
for explorers nowadays. My career advisor at school
للمستكشفين هذه الأيام. مستشار حياتي المهنية في المدرسة
never mentioned it as an option.
لم يذكر لي أبدًا الاستكشاف كخيار.
If I wanted to know, for example,
إذا أردت أن أعلم، على سبيل المثال،
how many stars were in the Milky Way,
كم كان عدد النجوم في درب التبانة،
how old those giant heads on Easter Island were,
كم كان عمر الرؤوس الكبيرة في جزيرة إيستر،
most of you could find that out right now
أغلبكم سيعرف هذه المعلومات في اللحظة
without even standing up.
حتى بدون أن تقف.
And yet, if I've learned anything in nearly 12 years now
وبهذا، إذا كنت قد تعلمت أي شيء خلال 12 عاما المنصرمة
of dragging heavy things around cold places,
من سحب أشياء ثقيلة في الأماكن الباردة
it is that true, real inspiration and growth
هو أن الإلهام الحقيقي والنمو
only comes from adversity and from challenge,
يأتي فقط من الشدة و التحدي،
from stepping away from what's comfortable and familiar
من الابتعاد عما هو مريح ومعروف
and stepping out into the unknown.
والمضي إلى المجهول.
In life, we all have tempests to ride and poles to walk to,
في الحياة، كلنا لدينا محاولات للركوب وأقطاب للمشي فيها،
and I think metaphorically speaking, at least,
وأنا أعتقد بالحديث مجازاً، في الأخير،
we could all benefit from getting outside the house
كلنا نستطيع الاستفادة من الخروج من المنزل
a little more often, if only we could summon up the courage.
إذا استطعنا أن نجمع الشجاعة.
I certainly would implore you to open the door just a little bit
أنا حاليا أدعوكم لتفتحوا الباب ولو قليلا
and take a look at what's outside.
وتنظروا إلى الخارج.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)